<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Malk’Zameth’s Braindump]]></title>
  <link href="http://malk.zameth.org/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://malk.zameth.org/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-31T15:12:22+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://malk.zameth.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Malk’Zameth]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What does it means for a Datastore to be elastic?]]></title>
    <link href="http://malk.zameth.org/blog/2012/10/31/what-does-it-means-for-a-datastore-to-be-elastic/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-31T13:57:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://malk.zameth.org/blog/2012/10/31/what-does-it-means-for-a-datastore-to-be-elastic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>What does it means for a Datastore to be <em>elastic</em>?</h2>

<h3>In 140 Characters or less</h3>

<p>Elastic datastores handle <em>stress</em> losing neither <em>consistency</em> nor <em>availability</em>.</p>

<h3>In detail</h3>

<p>To understand that one need to understand what is <em>Elasticity</em> exactly!</p>

<h4>So, What is <em>elasticity</em> ?</h4>

<p>We have two kinds of elasticity</p>

<h5>General Elasticity</h5>

<pre><code>Ability of *something* to receive a *stress* without deforming.
</code></pre>

<p>Think about a rubber band: you can take it with your hands, stretch it
and abandon it : the band will return to its original shape.</p>

<p>Commonly used in physics.</p>

<h5>Point elasticity</h5>

<pre><code>*rate* of how much *something* follows another.
</code></pre>

<p>Think about two objects, attached to each other by a rubber band :
when one of them moves, the other follows. Not immediately, not in the
same speed (because in the beginning the rubber band will stretch
instead of pull) but follows anyway.</p>

<p>Commonly used in mathematics.</p>

<h4>What is an <em>Elastic</em> ?</h4>

<p><em>Something</em> with a <em>high</em> elasticity.</p>

<h4>So, when is a datastore elastic?</h4>

<p>When it shows, in any form, a high degree of <em>elasticity</em>. Here are some common examples:</p>

<h5>Scaling up and down</h5>

<p>If we consider the <em>General elasticity</em> :</p>

<pre><code>Ability of *something* to receive a *stress* without deforming.
</code></pre>

<p>Our <em>something</em> is the datastore, its <em>stress</em> is the force of a high
number of concurrent users (say: your blog got featured highly on
reddit).</p>

<p>The datastore would be elastic if it <em>both</em>:</p>

<ol>
<li>Scaled up during the stress of that spike in number of visits (say:
used more nodes in the cluster).</li>
<li>Scaled down after the spike back to its original form (say:
returned by himself to its original number of nodes)</li>
</ol>


<p>Not scaling at all would of course not qualify as elastic, but only
scaling up is not enough.</p>

<h5><em>Accepting</em> schema changes</h5>

<p>Again we consider the <em>General elasticity</em> :</p>

<pre><code>Ability of *something* to receive a *stress* without deforming.
</code></pre>

<p>Our <em>something</em> : the datastore. Its stress : The data schema changes a lot.</p>

<p>Here our datastore would be elastic if it could handle the changes of
schema on the data and always use its own schema in the end.</p>

<p>This is possible in datastores that are effectively schema-less (like mongo)</p>

<h5><em>Adapting to</em> schema changes</h5>

<p>Let’s revisit the same “the data schema changes a lot” problem, but
this time we use <em>point elasticity</em>:</p>

<pre><code>*rate* of how much *something* follows *another*.
</code></pre>

<p>The datastore would be elastic if it would be able to take the new
data schema into consideration and (after some time) evolve its own
schema to handle the difference.</p>

<p>This is the approach used by Graph databases to handle the emergence of
relationships that are unknown initially.</p>

<h3>Remember</h3>

<p>Every Elastic has its <em>Yield strength</em> : the point of wich, the
<em>stress</em> is just too much and the <em>elastic</em> loses all <em>elasticity</em>.
Every rubber band has a point where it breaks.</p>

<p>You should seek the <em>Yield strength</em> of your datastore system under
your production architecture•</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimum Viable PaaS?]]></title>
    <link href="http://malk.zameth.org/blog/2012/10/22/minimum-viable-paas/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-22T12:05:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://malk.zameth.org/blog/2012/10/22/minimum-viable-paas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>What is a Minimum Viable PaaS?</h2>

<h3>In one tweet</h3>

<p>A what point an IaaS becomes a PaaS? When you forget there is an IaaS at all.</p>

<h3>Basis</h3>

<p>We all know the theory, the cloud mainly is broken into:</p>

<ul>
<li>IaaS - Infrastructure as a Service (Amazon, OpenStack, etc.)</li>
<li>PaaS - Platform as a Service (Heroku, Cloudbees, etc.)</li>
<li>SaaS - Software as a Service (Salesforce, Office 365, etc.)</li>
</ul>


<p>IaaS brings machines, memories, CPU&#8217;s, systems.</p>

<p>PaaS brings integration:</p>

<ul>
<li>Usually as system integration (Abstracting away the infrastructure).</li>
<li>Maybe as architecture/applicative integration (Bringing Blocks that
are not only used but compose the deployed product).</li>
<li>Maybe as a development application (selling support to oil-up your
dev process).</li>
</ul>


<h3>Doubts</h3>

<p>What the several PaaS offers do actually provide is fluctuting.</p>

<p>The IaaS providers themselves do offer some level of integration (some enter deeply into PaaS-land without really becoming one).</p>

<p>So: What is the minimal set of features that make a PaaS a PasS?</p>

<p>What is the minimum viable PaaS?</p>

<h3>My jab at an answer</h3>

<p>My minimum feature set would be:</p>

<h4>IaaS brokerage</h4>

<p>If the PaaS is not an IaaS it should have a way to communicate with one! Which is a given: Nothing revolutionary.</p>

<h4>IaaS abstraction</h4>

<p>The PaaS user do not want to control how much CPU it needs, neither how much memory nor what OS does his virtual machine uses nor that it uses virtual machines at all.</p>

<p>He wants to deploy a product to the platform and have it &#8220;magically&#8221; handle those details.</p>

<p>Or failing that at least take sensible defaults for everything and mostly &#8220;just work&#8221;.</p>

<h4>Product installation</h4>

<p>A corollary of <em>IaaS Abstraction</em> is that the end-user does not deploy a virtual machine, but his product only. His deploying interface is product oriented.</p>

<h4>Product finding</h4>

<p>At least internally, if the unit of a PaaS is a product, it should be able to find where its products are.</p>

<h4>Simple scalability as a Service</h4>

<p>Regardless of the PaaS&#8217; own Supervision the user should be able to manually ask for more resources should a sudden need of scalability arise.</p>

<p>IaaS should do that too, but PaaS should hide the &#8220;how&#8221;: the user should ask for more horsepower, without worrying what that horsepower is (machines, memory etc.)</p>

<h4>Load balancing as a Service</h4>

<p>At some point scaling will mean having a product turn on several machines, the PaaS should load balance betwen those.</p>

<h4>Monitoring</h4>

<p>Not something highly developed (like loggly) but at least a way to know your product is down.</p>

<h4>Configuration management</h4>

<p>Not as an external service, but the brunt work of a PaaS is giving a working system completely configured.</p>

<p>That configuration will evolve, in all deployed systems.</p>

<p>The PaaS will need high amounts of configuration management (using tools like puppet or chef probably)</p>

<h3>What would be your answer?</h3>

<p>Candid feedback welcome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[About]]></title>
    <link href="http://malk.zameth.org/blog/2012/10/16/about/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://malk.zameth.org/blog/2012/10/16/about</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Malk’Zameth’s Braindump</h2>

<p>Random serialisations of things in my brain: Grown for my usage. Maybe gibberish to you! <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/deed.en_GB">Feel free to use it</a>. Comments welcome•</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
